Lee-Palfrey Families Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Lee-Palfrey Families Papers 1780-1932 (bulk 1800-1860)
MSS65612
Lee family
Palfrey family
1,500 items
4 containers
1.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, diaries, journals, clippings, maps, photographs, and other papers of William Lee (1772-1840) of Boston, Massachusetts, Washington, D.C., and France and members of his family. Of particular interest are Lee's diaries and letters detailing his experiences as a commercial agent and secretary to the United States Legation in France. Also includes a journal and photographs of a topographical mission to Utah in 1858-1859 by a descendent, William Lee (1841-1893).
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Kalisky, Louisa, active 1823-1827. Louisa Kalisky papers.; Lee family.; Lee, Susan Palfrey, 1767-1822. Susan Palfrey Lee papers.; Lee, Susan Palfrey, 1795-1853. Susan Palfrey Lee papers.; Lee, William Barlow, 1805-1895. William Barlow Lee papers.; Lee, William, 1772-1840. William Lee papers.; Lee, William, 1841-1893. William Lee papers.; Maltitz, Mary Elizabeth Lee, Baroness de, 1799-1852. Mary Elizabeth Lee, Baroness de Maltitz, papers.; Palfrey family.
Organizations
United States. Legation (France)
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, American--France.; Topographical surveying--Utah.
Places
France--Commerce--United States.; France--Foreign relations--United States.; France--Social life and customs.; United States--Commerce--France.; United States--Commerce--History--19th century.; United States--Foreign relations--France.; Utah--Description and travel.; Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs.
Provenance
The papers of the Lee-Palfrey families were given to the Library of Congress by Mary Lee Mann, 1948-1958.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of the Lee-Palfrey families are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the Lee-Palfrey families span the years 1780-1932, with the bulk of the material from 1800 to 1860. The collection consists of correspondence, diaries, journals, clippings, maps, photographs, and other papers of William Lee (1772-1840) of Boston, Massachusetts, Washington, D.C., and France and members of his family. Of particular interest are Lee's diaries and letters detailing his experiences as a commercial agent and secretary to the United States Legation in France.
Included in the collection are papers of Lee's wife, Susan Palfrey Lee (1767-1822), relating to family matters and social life in France and Washington, D.C.; papers of his daughters, Susan Palfrey Lee (1795-1853) and Mary Elizabeth Lee, Baroness de Maltitz (1799-1852), and his son William Barlow Lee (1805-1895). A journal of William Barlow Lee's son, William Lee, a Washington, D.C., physician and teacher (1841-1893) relates to a topographical mission to Utah in 1857-1858 in which he served as an assistant to J. H. Simpson in surveying a wagon route from Camp Floyd to Salt Lake City. Included are photographs from the mission.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material and therein by name of family member.
Container List
- Diaries, William Lee (1772-1840), 1796, 1797-180l, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Memorandum book, William Lee (1772-1840), l794-1816 (Box 1)
- Journals (Box 1)
  - William Lee (1841-1893), 1858-1859 (Box 1)
  - Louisa Kalisky, incomplete translation of German diary, 1823-1824 (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - William Lee I, 1791-1794 (Box 1)
  - Mary Lee I, 1793-1794 (Box 1)
  - William Lee (1772-1840) (Box 1)
    - 1802-1816, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1820-1837, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Susan Palfrey Lee (1767-1822), 1793-1821 (Box 2)
  - William Palfrey, 1790-1812 (Box 2)
  - John Palfrey, 1786-1820 (Box 2)
  - Mary Palfrey, 1798 (Box 2)
  - Mary Lee II, 1790-1793 (Box 2)
  - William Barlow Lee (1805-1895), 1816-1830 (Box 2)
  - Mary Elizabeth Lee Maltitz, Baroness de, 1812-1840, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Susan Lee (1795-1853), 1829-1830, undated (Box 3)
  - William Lee (1841-1893), 1883-1885 (Box 3)
  - Mary Lee Mann, 1900-1932, undated (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous family correspondence, 1789-1866 (Box 3)
- General correspondence (Box 3)
  - 1780-1850, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Undated (Box 4)
- Photographs of trip to Utah by William Lee (1841-1893), 1858-1859 (Box 4)
- Photographs of family members, undated (Box 4)
- Maps, 1858-1859 (?) (Box 4)
- Newspaper clippings, 1858-1859 (Box 4)